Irena Urdang deTour Collection of Holocaust Materials 2006.0172
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Irena Urdang deTour Collection of Holocaust Materials.
undated, 1975-2012.
2006.0172
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
9.0 Linear feet
The collection contains a few personal materials pertaining to her experiences as well as publications, newsletters, invitations and other documents from Holocaust survivor and support organizations in the United States collected by Mrs. DeTour.
deTour, Irena Urdang.
Biography
Irena Urdang de Tour was born in Warsaw, Poland, the daughter of Seweryn Ehrlich vel Sluszny and Felicja (Lubelczyk) Ehrlich. In November 1940, she was confined, with her parents and sister Danuta, to the Warsaw Ghetto where she worked in an Electropol factory. She escaped the ghetto to the Christian section of Warsaw in March 1943, where she acquired false documents and worked as a maid. In September 1944 she joined the underground, building barricades, organizing shelters, and working for the Red Cross. Following the suppression of the uprising, she was sent to a slave labor camp in Berlin with her aunt who also possessed false documents. There she worked in the Schwartzkopf factory manufactoring war material. At the end of the war de Tour walked to Warsaw to search for family members. Her father had died in the Warsaw uprising, and she and her mother and sister were placed in the Bindermichl Displaced Persons Camp in Linz, Austria, where she worked for the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration as an interpreter and secretary. In July 1946 the family left for New York City. De Tour was employed as a bookkeeper, secretary, buyer, and was a fiction and feature editor for Town and Country, Gourmet, and the Paris Review. In 1952 she married Laurence Urdang, a lexicographer; they had two daughters, Alexandra and Nicole. She received her B.A. from Hunter College in 1956. A writer and poet, de Tour also ran an antiques business for many years and was involved in a number of charitable organizations, including CARE.
Biographical information posted by the Jewish Women's Archive [accessed 6/8/2011].
Additional de Tour materials can be found at the Museum of Jewish Heritage; Jewish Women's Archive; and Schlesinger Library, Radcliffe Institute, among others.
Scope and Content
The collection contains publications, announcements, conference materials, invitations, book reviews, obituaries and other items collected by Mrs. DeTour.
Arrangement
Series I: Biography ( undated )
Series II: People ( undated, 1991-2007 )
Series III: Subjects ( undated, 1981-2009 )
Series IV: Organizations (Publications, calendars, correspondence) ( undated, 1991-2009 )
Series V: Conferences and Remembrances ( 1995-2009 )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to various aspects of Connecticut history. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Blood Lines Dodd A6802
Warsaw Ghetto Dodd
The Last Word Dodd
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The materials in the collection have been donated periodically by Mrs. DeTour beginning in 2006.
deTour, Irena Urdang;; Books.; Correspondence.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Holocaust survivors--Correspondence.; Newsletters.; Newspapers.; Notes.; Obituaries.; Photocopies.; Press releases.; Publications.
- Series I: Biographical Materials, undated (Box 1)
  - Biography (portions from original located at Hunter College, photocopy), undated (Box 1)
- Series II: People, undated, 1991-2007 (Box 1)
  - Anger, Per, 2002 (Box 1)
  - Bell, Daniella, undated, 1999-2006
  - Bukety, Melvin, 2005
  - Fisher, Regine, 1995
  - Hackel, Shirley, 2000
  - Hruza, Judita, 1996-1999
  - [Irena's friends from Displaced Persons conference], 1993-2006
  - Korczak, Janus, undated, 1993
  - Metcalf, Linda T., 1991
  - Piatka, Naava, 1996-1999
  - Rinkel, Elfriede, 2006
  - Strochlitz, Sigmund, 2006-2007
  - Wiesenthal, Simon, 2005
- Series III: Subjects, undated, 1981-2009 (Box 1)
  - Auschwitz (and other) camp, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Books, resources and clippings, undated, 1997-2009
  - Boston Area Holocaust Matters, undated
  - Children of Survivors, 2008
  - Confiscated Art, 2008
  - Events, 2007-2008
  - Holocaust Resources, 2007-2008
  - Home Care for Survivors, 2008
  - Irena's Vow, 2008
  - Memorials, undated, 2007-2008
  - Movies, 2008-2009
  - Obituaries, 2006-2009
  - Periodicals and Pamphlets, 1992-2009 (Box 4)
  - Poland, 1981-1994 (Box 1)
  - Post Traumatic Stress Disorder, 1995-2000
  - Restitution - Hardship Fund Claims, 1999-2008
  - Rosa - Hartford Stage, 2008
  - Shiron, undated
  - Shoah Memorials, 2006
  - Survivor Stories, 2007-2009
  - Undying Love, 2000-2004
- Series IV: Organizations (publications, calendars, correspondence), undated, 1991-2009
  - All Generations, 2006 (Box 1)
  - American Jewish Historical Society, 2004-2009 (Box 1)
  - American Society for Yad Vashem, undated (Box 1)
  - Anti-Defamation League, 2005-2008 (Box 1)
  - Auschwitz Jewish Center Foundation, 2000-2002 (Box 1)
  - Blue Card, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Chabad Educational Institute, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Chabad of Southampton Jewish Center, 2007-2008 (Box 1)
  - Chabad's Children Chernobyl, undated (Box 1)
  - Children's Village of Jerusalem, 2002-2009 (Box 1)
  - Chmol, 2003-2004 (Box 1)
  - Facing History in Ourselves, 1996-1999 (Box 1)
  - Federation of Polish Jews, 2006-2007 (Box 1)
  - Fortunoff Video Archives (Yale), 1992 (Box 1)
  - Friends of the Israel Defense Forces, 2002 (Box 1)
  - General Israel Orphan's Home for Girls, 2002-2003 (Box 1)
  - Hatikva Museum, 1999-2006 (Box 1)
  - Irena's Vow, 2008 (Box 2)
  - Hidden Child Foundation, 1997-2009 (Box 2)
  - Holocaust Child Survivors of Connecticut, 2007-2009 (Box 2)
  - Holocaust Resource Center & Archives (CUNY-QCC), undated, 2002 (Box 2)
  - International Fellowship of Christians and Jews, 2008 (Box 2)
  - Janus Koczak Society of America, 1992-1995 (Box 2)
  - Jewish foundation for the Righteous, 2003-2009 (Box 2)
  - Jewish War Veterans of the USA, 2003-2004 (Box 2)
  - Kinder Transport Association, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Moshe Rynecki Virtual Museum, 2007 (Box 2)
  - Museum of Jewish Heritage, 1998-2009 (Box 2)
  - National Association of Jewish Child Holocaust Survivors--NAHOS, 1999-2007 (Box 2)
  - National Association of Jewish Child Holocaust Survivors--NAHOS--Slave Labor, 2003 (Box 2)
  - National Yiddish Book Center, 2007-2009 (Box 2)
  - New Haven Memorial of Memory and Legacy, 2008 (Box 2)
  - Ohr Torah Stone, undated (Box 2)
  - ORT America, 2008 (Box 2)
  - Raoul Wallenberg Committee of the US, 2007-2009 (Box 2)
  - Schoen Books, 1997-2007 (Box 2)
  - Shoah Visual History Foundation, 1994-2000 (Box 2)
  - Simon Wiesenthal Center, undated (Box 2)
  - Together, 2001-2009 (Box 2)
  - US Holocaust Memorial Museum, 1989-2009 (Box 2)
  - Wallenberg Foundation, 2003 (Box 3)
  - Whole Megillah, 2007 (Box 3)
  - World Jewish Congress, 2001-2007 (Box 3)
  - Yivo Institute, 2001-2009 (Box 3)
- Series V: Conferences and Remembrances, 1995-2009
  - 50 Years...of Life after the Holocaust, 1995 (Box 3)
  - Child Survivors of the Holocaust, 2001, 2006 (Box 3)
  - International Child Survivors and Second Generation Conference, 2000, 2002, 2006, 2009 (Box 3)
  - International Day of Commemoration, 2006 (Box 3)
  - Life Reborn, Jewish Displaced Persons Conference, 2000 (Box 3)
  - Living the Legacy (Descendents of the Shoah), Chicago, 2002 (Box 3)
  - National Association of Jewish Child Holocaust Survivors -- NAHOS, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Tribute to Holocaust Survivors, 2003 (Box 3)
  - Map of Lwov, undated (Box 4)
- Series VI: 2010-2011 Additions (Box 5)
  Scope and Contents note
  Publications, invitations, clippings and notes related to Hidden child and Holocaust focused organizations.
- Series VII: 2012 Additions, 1975-2012
  - Holocaust, hidden child, second generation related publications, articles, clippings and memorabilia, correspondence, notes, publications, reviews, 2007-2012 (Box 6)
  - Holocaust, hidden child, second generation related publications, articles, clippings and memorabilia, correspondence, notes, publications, reviews, 2006-2012 (Box 7)